<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="ext_image_capture_source_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2022 Andri Yngvason
    Copyright © 2024 Simon Ser

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="opaque image capture source objects">
    This protocol serves as an intermediary between capturing protocols and
    potential image capture sources such as outputs and toplevels.

    This protocol may be extended to support more image capture sources in the
    future, thereby adding those image capture sources to other protocols that
    use the image capture source object without having to modify those
    protocols.

    Warning! The protocol described in this file is currently in the testing
    phase. Backward compatible changes may be added together with the
    corresponding interface version bump. Backward incompatible changes can
    only be done by creating a new major version of the extension.
  </description>

  <interface name="ext_image_capture_source_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="opaque image capture source object">
      The image capture source object is an opaque descriptor for a capturable
      resource.  This resource may be any sort of entity from which an image
      may be derived.

      Note, because ext_image_capture_source_v1 objects are created from multiple
      independent factory interfaces, the ext_image_capture_source_v1 interface is
      frozen at version 1.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="delete this object">
        Destroys the image capture source. This request may be sent at any time
        by the client.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_output_image_capture_source_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="image capture source manager for outputs">
      A manager for creating image capture source objects for wl_output objects.
    </description>

    <request name="create_source">
      <description summary="create source object for output">
        Creates a source object for an output. Images captured from this source
        will show the same content as the output. Some elements may be omitted,
        such as cursors and overlays that have been marked as transparent to
        capturing.
      </description>
      <arg name="source" type="new_id" interface="ext_image_capture_source_v1"/>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="delete this object">
        Destroys the manager. This request may be sent at any time by the client
        and objects created by the manager will remain valid after its
        destruction.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="ext_foreign_toplevel_image_capture_source_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="image capture source manager for foreign toplevels">
      A manager for creating image capture source objects for
      ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1 objects.
    </description>

    <request name="create_source">
      <description summary="create source object for foreign toplevel">
        Creates a source object for a foreign toplevel handle. Images captured
        from this source will show the same content as the toplevel.
      </description>
      <arg name="source" type="new_id" interface="ext_image_capture_source_v1"/>
      <arg name="toplevel_handle" type="object" interface="ext_foreign_toplevel_handle_v1"/>
    </request>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="delete this object">
        Destroys the manager. This request may be sent at any time by the client
        and objects created by the manager will remain valid after its
        destruction.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
